Guide to the Video Free Earth Production Company records, 1971-1991 MS2041
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Video Free Earth Production Company records
1971-1991
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2041
18 Linear Feet
Collection contains videos, production files, general business files, personal and business correspondence, scripts, photographs, slides, and negatives. The material dates from 1983-89. The collection documents the work of late gay artist Jamie Walters.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Video Free Earth Production Company Collection was donated to the Gelman Library in 1996 by Mr. Kenneth Rothschild and Mr. Leonard Braverman. It is part of the Gay and Lesbian History Archives of the Special Collections Department.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series: Leonard Braverman papers, and Kenneth Rothschild papers.
Biographical Note
The Video Free Earth Production Company was founded in 1982 as a broadcast and commercial videotape company, and the collection chronicles video work of Washington, D.C. dramatic and performance artists. The company was co-founded by Jamie Walters and Leonard Braverman.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains videos, production files, general business files, personal and business correspondence, scripts, photographs, slides, and negatives. The material dates from 1983-89. The collection documents the work of late gay artist Jamie Walters. Walters scripted, directed, and performed numerous satirical pieces designed for video. His work was exhibited in a number of galleries, including the Tate Gallery in London. The collection documents the innovative development and exploration of video to produce artwork.
Color slides; Photographs; Black-and-white slides; Performance art; Gays; Video tape collections; Washington (D.C.); Political satire; Lesbians -- Washington (D.C.); Gay men -- Washington (D.C.); Walters, Jamie; Braverman, Leonard; Rothschild, Kenneth; Gaver, Chasen; Video Free Earth Production Company
- Leonard Braverman papers, 1971-1990; MS2041 Series 1; 11 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of videotapes, photographs, and printed material. The years cover 1971-90. These include performance poetry by Chasen Gaver, and satirical looks at Joan Kennedy (ex-wife of Senator Ted Kennedy), D.C. Mayor Marion Barry. A number of other social and political topics are lampooned. The printed material consists of production files, public relations files, photographs, and some oversized items (mostly 11x14" photographs). The production files deal with the various films made by Video Free Earth, and include scripts, editing logs, story boards, correspondence, resumés, newspaper clippings, grant applications, and budgets. Many of these videos were written and directed by Jamie Walters, the co-founder of the company along with Mr. Braverman.
  - Videotapes: Artists in Collaboration - 1 cassette (VHS), 1989 (Box 2B, Videocassette 1)
    General note
    [From original finding aid]: c. 20 min.; original tape 1; Act I of 11/18/1989 performance. Includes program listing of dance performances
  - Videotapes: Artists in Collaboration - 1 cassette (VHS), 1989 (Box 2B, Videocassette 2)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 40 min.; original tape 2; Act II of 11/18/1989 performance. Recording of dance pieces performed at the Publick Playhouse. Performers include members of the D.C. Contemporary Dance Theater, Jubilation Dance Company and Philadelphia Dance Company
  - Videotapes: Babazaar Aziz - 1 cassette (VHS); original tape 1, 1989 September 23 (Box 2B, Videocassette 3)
  - Videotapes: Babazaar Aziz - 1 cassette (VHS); original tape 2, 1989 September 23 (Box 2B, Videocassette 4)
  - Videotapes: Babazaar Aziz - 1 cassette (VHS); original tape 3, 1989 September 23 (Box 2B, Videocassette 5)
    [From original finding aid]: on cassette label: Gay. Video by Jamie Walters and Leonard Braverman. Records Babazaar Aziz, a multi-media arts event, which was held on Saturday September 23, 1989 at the Market 5 Gallery. There are poetry readings, musical performances and various visual arts media
  - Videotapes: Beat: The Performance Poetry of Chasen Gaver - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 1B, Videocassette 6)
    [From original finding aid]: dubbing master; audio on channels 1 & 2; flat mono mix; on cassette label: from 1 inch unmixed copy; VFE Productions
  - Videotapes: Beat: The Performance Poetry of Chasen Gaver - 1 reel (2 inch), undated (Box 1A, Reel 7)
    [From original finding aid]: master; n.s; mixed audio, both channels; VFE Productions
  - Videotapes: Beat: The Performance Poetry of Chasen Gaver - 1 reel (2 inch), Circa 1988 (Box 1A, Reel 8)
    [From original finding aid]: edited master; 28 min; unmixed audio, channels 1 & 2. (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 3). Documents the innovative ways in which Washington writer/poet Chasen Gaver uses movement, percussion and other performance elements to enhance the delivery of verse. He uses this form of poetry to raise questions about our society, encourage cross-cultural awareness and make us reflect on contemporary issues
  - Videotapes: The Bike Pants Phenomenon - 1 cassette (VHS), 1989 (Box 2B, Videocassette 9)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 13 min.; edit master; VFE Productions; Jamie Walters. (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no.3)
  - Videotapes: The Boat - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 2A, Videocassette 10)
    [From original finding aid]: master with titles; Feb. 1986; 2:35 min. (NOTE: also on Video Salon I Tape, Compilation Tape no. 3, and Mayor's Show). By Chasen Gaver; directed by Jamie Walters; video by Leonard Braverman. This is Gaver's punk poem about the battle of the human spirit against the story waves of life. As Gaver points out, "some people miss the boat."
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 1 - 1 cassette (VHS), 1980-1982 (Box 2B, Dvd 1, Videocassette 11)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 41 min.; master. First Lady Joan (NOTE: also on Compilation Tapes no. 5 and 6, Jamie Walters Retrospective and Performance Pastiche). By Jamie Walters; with Jamie Walters and Jack Guidone1980; c.28 min. A parody of American domestic and political life. Barbara Walters interviews Joan Kennedy. Assuming a reconciliation with Ted this acerbic farce casts alcoholic, manic depressive Joan Kennedy as first lady. First segment of "A Kennedy Trilogy." Joan Comes Home (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 5 and 6, Jamie Walters Retrospective). Directed by David Vanderbilt; written by Jamie Walters 1980; 5 min. In this abrasive concluding segment of "A Kennedy Trilogy," Joan returns to the White House after hospital treatment. Jackie Strikes Back (NOTE: also on Compilation Tapes no. 5 and 6, Jamie Walters Retrospective). Directed by Jamie Walters; written by Chasen Gaver 1982; 7 min. A spoof on Jacqueline Onassis's possible telephone response to First Lady Joan. Second segment of "A Kennedy Trilogy."
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 2 - 1 cassette (VHS), Circa 1990 (Box 2B, Videocassette 12)
    [From original finding aid]: 8:37 min.; note: the first two works together run c. 8:13 min. with 4 seconds between them and the program starts 2:05 min. into the tape. They Said She Had Balls (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 7 and in Series II, Videotape no. 12) Save the Arts Phillie Titans (NOTE: also on Compilation Tapes no. 7 and in Series II, Videotape no. 12): c. 20 min
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 3 - 1 cassette (VHS), 1982-1984 (Box 2B, Videocassette 13)
    [From original finding aid]: on container label: 1; contains the following: Baja Fantasy (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 9). Directed and written by Jamie Walters; music by Flaco Jimenez 1984; 4 min. An exciting juxtaposition of ideas, where we discover daydreaming or reality. A visual and musical interpretation of a dream about yearning to return to a distant "mental oasis." Film from the Mexican Baja is blended with video of a young man reading, showering and doing garden chores. Beat (description in Series I, Tape 8). The Bike Pants Phenomenon (description in Series I, Tape 9). The Boat (description in Series I, Tape 10). Capitol Hill - 1982; c. 6 min. (NOTE: also on Compilation Tapes no. 6 and 8, and Jamie Walters Retrospective). Directed by Jamie Walters; written by Joseph Lanz. Details the daily trials of a depressed Republican Senate aide, who struggles to work and is wronged by life at every turn. Cuckoo Clock (description in Series I, Tape 22). Crack Politician (description in Series I, Tape 20). Desk in Hell (description in Series I, Tape 23)
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 4 - 1 cassette (VHS), undated (Box 2B, Videocassette 14)
    [From original finding aid]: on container label: 2; contains the following: A Family All Together (description in Series I, Tape 24). A Family Five Years Later (description in Series I, Tape 27)
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 5 - 1 cassette (VHS), 1983-1987 (Box 2B, Videocassette 15)
    [From original finding aid]: on container label: 3 First Lady Joan (description in Series I, Tape 11). Joan Comes Home (description in Series I, Tape 11). Jackie Strikes Back (description in Series I, Tape 11). First Lady Joan-The Remake Directed by Leonard Braverman; written by Jamie Walters; 12 min.1982. Remake of 1980 version. Fresh Out of Ideas (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 9). By Jamie Walters and Chasen Gaver 1984; 2 min. Gaver is an actor rather than a reciter and pulls the "text" out of a gold-leaf skull, folds it into an airplane and then tosses it over and over. Scenes of newspaper production and World War II propaganda footage are intercut with this main action, echoing visually the rhythms of the poem. Gloria's Point of View (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 6). Directed and written by Jamie Walters 1984; 4 min. A satiric commentary of the media overkill that pervades our society. Gloria Vanderbilt reacts to Ronald Reagan's "Star Wars" speech as she has tea. Litany of Addresses (NOTE: also on Video Salon I and on Compilation tape no. 5; detailed description in Series I, Tape 56) By Isabel-Lee Malone; directed by Jamie Walters; 13 min.1987. Les Femmes Perdues Louise Nevelson Takes a Bath (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 8). Directed and written by Jamie Walters 1983; 3:30 min. Louise Nevelson is here portrayed as a droll transvestite. The sculptor discusses her life and perspectives on her work. Preparation H (description in Series I, Tape 38)
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 6 - 1 cassette (VHS), 1980-1982 (Box 2B, Videocassette 16)
    [From original finding aid]: on container label: 4; contains the following: Selection of Shorts Kennedy Trilogy (First Lady Joan, Jackie Strikes Back, Joan Comes Home) [description in Series I, Tape 11]. What a Poem Can Do? (NOTE: also on Jamie Walters Retrospective). Directed by David Vanderbilt and Leonard Braverman 1981; 2 min.. A segment from the first videotaped production of the performance poetry of Chasen Gaver. Johnny on the Spot (NOTE: also on Jamie Walters Retrospective). Performed by Darryl Bertolucci and Melanie Eisenberg 1982; 3 min. An improvisation skit. Desk in Hell (description in Series I, Tape 23). Capitol Hill (description in Series I, Tape 13). Those Farragut Women (NOTE: also on Jamie Walters Retrospective and Selection of Shorts). Directed by Tim McGaughey and Jay Crews 1980; 8 min. A pseudo-promotional trailer about the trials of women from 100 B.C. to the present as traced through the family tree of the Farraguts.Stay or Go
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 7 - 1 cassette (VHS), undated (Box 2B, Videocassette 17)
    [From original finding aid]: on container label: 5; contains the following:Thru the CRT (description in Series I, Tape 49);They Said She Had Balls;Phillie Titans;Under Suspicion (description in Series I, Tape 50);Vicki Picks a Tie (description in Series I, Tape 51);Video-D (description in series I, Tape 55);Real Estate Demo VFE Logo Tape
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 8 - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 2A, Videocassette 18)
    [From original finding aid]: master; Video Free Earth;Capitol Hill (description in Series I, Tape 13);Louise Nevelson Takes a Bath (description in Series I, Tape 15)
  - Videotapes: Compilation Tape no. 9 - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 2A, Videocassette 19)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 10 min.; master,contains the following: Fresh Out of Ideas (descriptionin Series I, Tape 15);Gloria's Point of View (description in Series I, Tape 15);Baja Fantasy (description in Series I, Tape 13)
  - Videotapes: Crack Politician - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); edit master, 1991 (Box 2B, Videocassette 20)
    [From original finding aid]: on cassette label: disclaimer after credits. (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no.3). Directed and written by Jamie Walters 1991; 10 minin. Satire on the rise and fall of D.C. mayor Marion Barry. Covers his rise from obscurity during the Civil Rights movement, through his relationships with wife Karen Johnson, Rasheeda Moore and his constituents, and his ultimate downfall
  - Videotapes: Cuckoo Clock - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), Circa 1985 (Box 2A, Videocassette 21)
    [From original finding aid]: 6:48 without titles; master
  - Videotapes: Cuckoo Clock - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1980 (Box 1B, Videocassette 22)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 44 min.; edit master; DCTV; on container label: for Walters Retrospective, producer, Jamie Walters. Direction and screenplay, L. Sugar-Cohen 1980. A parody of American domestic and political life. Marge Jones, a b-movie actress, is plagued by creditors and blackmail. She returns to her hometown, Zanesville, Ohio, to raise her two children and save herself
  - Videotapes: Desk in Hell - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1982 February (Box 1B, Videocassette 23)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 11 min.; color, stereo; master copy. (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 3 and Jamie Walters Retrospective). Directed by Gregory Forsd; written by Chasen Gaver
  - Videotapes: A Family Altogether - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 2A, Videocassette 24)
  - Videotapes: A Family Five Years Later - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1989 October (Box 1B, Videocassette 25)
    [From original finding aid]: SHT master
  - Videotapes: A Family Five Years Later - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), undated (Box 1B, Videocassette 26)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 80 min.; master 1; on cassette label: fast credits, includes phone ring
  - Videotapes: A Family Five Years Later - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1982 (Box 1B, Videocassette 27)
    [From original finding aid]: c. 80 min.; master 2; on cassette label: fast credits, control track laid. 1982; 56 min. A sequel to A Family Altogether
  - Videotapes: First Lady Joan, undated (Box 2B, Videocassette 28)
    [From original finding aid]: Remake master - 1 cassette (VHS)
  - Videotapes: Gay and Lesbian Pride Day, Washington, D.C., 1988 June (Box 2B, Videocassette 29)
    [From original finding aid]: edit master - 1 cassette (VHS)
  - Videotapes: Georgetown University Dance Company Fall Performance -, 1989 December (Box 2B, Videocassette 30)
    [From original finding aid]: original 1 cassette (VHS)
  - Videotapes: Human Rights Campaign Fund Safety - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1984 April (Box 1B, Videocassette 31)
    [From original finding aid]: safety master; on cassette label: D.C. shoot; includes shot list
  - Videotapes: Jamie Walters Retrospective - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1982 (Box 2A, Videocassette 32)
    [From original finding aid]: edit master; DCTV; credits: producer, Jamie Walters; note: running time on container label: 13:18 min.; contains the following: Introduction (: 21 sec.): First Lady Joan (12:46 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 11];Jackie Strikes Back (5:43 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 11];Joan Comes Home (4:06 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 11];Chasen Gaver: What a Poem Can Do? (2:24 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 16];Johnny on the Spot [description in Series I, Tape 16];Desk in Hell (10:56 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 23];Capitol Hill (5:59 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 13];Those Farragut Women (6:01 min.) [description in Series I, Tape 16]
  - Videotapes: Joan Kennedy Story - 1 reel (1 inch), undated (Box 1A, Reel 33)
  - Videotapes: Litany of Addresses - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), undated (Box 2A, Videocassette 34)
    [From original finding aid]: color corrected master (description in Series 1, Tape 56)
  - Videotapes: Mayor's Show - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1986 June (Box 1B, Videocassette 35)
    [From original finding aid]: VFE Video Free Earth: The Boat (description in Series I, Tape 10);Vicki Picks a Tie (description in Series I, Tape 51);Thru the CRT [excerpt] (description in Series I, Tape 49)
  - Videotapes: Paul Flood's Arlington Arts Center Show - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1982 September (Box 2A, Videocassette 36)
    [From original finding aid]: on cassette label: Paul Flood at Arlington Arts Center
  - Videotapes: Performance Pastiche: the collections of Jack Guidone - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1986-1988 (Box 2A, Videocassette 37)
    [From original finding aid]: 12 min. 35 sec. 1988; audio on 1 and 2 unmixed; credits: edited by Jamie Walters; special thanks to Leonard Braverman, VFE Productions, Linda Lewett, John Woods, Michelle Ana (?), Joy of Motion; contains the following works: Dance in Silence (1985);Out of Control (NOTE: also on Video Salon I). By Jack Guidone; directed by Jamie Walters; 1985 ca.; 3 min.. This last performance on tape by Guidone is a documentation of a stage performance. His multi-media works included dance, improvisation, mime, and movement;A Family Five Years Later (1981) (description in Series I, Tape 11);First Lady Joan (1982) (description in Series I, Tape 11);Video-D (1983) (description in series I, Tape 55);Recipe for a Hot Planet (1986)
  - Videotapes: Preparation H - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); master with titles, 1986 (Box 2A, Videocassette 38)
    [From original finding aid]: on container labelJamie talent demo (NOTE: on Video Salon I and Compilation Tape no. 5). By Jamie Walters; directed by Hunter Wolkoff; 1 min. 1986. To think in one minute one may learn so many uses of this product. Walters plays all the characters
  - Videotapes: Real Estate Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1985 March (Box 2A, Videocassette 39)
    [From original finding aid]: 8:46; master; (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 7): by Jamie Walters and Leonard Braverman 1985. Promotes the making of videotapes to sell houses and properties
  - Videotapes: Stay or Go - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1986 September (Box 1B, Videocassette 40)
    [From original finding aid]: 48:15 min; master
  - Videotapes: Talent Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); original tape 1, 1985 April (Box 1A, Videocassette 41)
    [From original finding aid]: VFE Production
  - Videotapes: Talent Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); original tape 2, 1985 July (Box 1A, Videocassette 42)
    [From original finding aid]: VFE Productions
  - Videotapes: Talent Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); original tape 3, undated (Box 1A, Videocassette 43)
  - Videotapes: Talent Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); original tape 4, undated (Box 1A, Videocassette 44)
  - Videotapes: Talent Demo - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); original tape 5, 1986 (Box 1A, Videocassette 45)
    [From original finding aid]: VFE Productions. on container label: see VFE stock tape 7 VHS copy. Script by Jamie Walters 1986. Promotes the making of videotapes to market the talents of actors, artists, musicians and others
  - Videotapes: Thru the CRT - 1 reel (1 inch); edit master, undated (Box 2A, Reel 46)
    [From original finding aid]: unmixed 2 track; VFE Productions; Jamie Walters; no. 2
  - Videotapes: Thru the CRT - 1 reel (1 inch) (c. 25 min.); submaster, 1985 March 19 (Box 1A, Reel 47)
    [From original finding aid]: dub, time coded, 2 channel unmixed
  - Videotapes: Thru the CRT - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic); submaster, Circa 1985 (Box 1B, Videocassette 48)
    [From original finding aid]: Jamie Walters
  - Videotapes: Thru the CRT - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic) (c. 25 min.); dub 1, 1985 (Box 1B, Videocassette 49)
    [From original finding aid]: a Video Free Earth Production (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 7 and Mayor's Show). Directed and written by Jamie Walters 1985; 25 min. Walters uses a wide range of experimental video effects. It is a collage of video effects exploring television's impact on the human psyche
  - Videotapes: Under Suspicion - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic); master edit, 1984 June (Box 2A, Videocassette 50)
    [From original finding aid]: on cassette label: channel 2 - bars and sound track, channel - music, 2nd generation master edit, video/audio channel 2. Under Suspicion: by Jamie Walters and Chasen Gaver (NOTE: also on Compilation Tape no. 7). The poet vanishes and only his voice remains. He is replaced, as Walters describes it, by a "visual realization" of the poem's themes of spies, secret codes and lurking violence
  - Videotapes: Vicki Picks a Tie - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic); master, 1984 November (Box 2A, Videocassette 51)
    [From original finding aid]: 12 min; (NOTE: on Mayor's Show and Video Salon I). By Hunter Wolkoff; video by Leonard Braverman; 1984. This is a video fantasy about Vicki Morgan, scandalous ex-lover of Alfred Bloomingdale. Vicki thoughtfully goes shopping--to beat the heat
  - Videotapes: VFE Logo Tape - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic), 1986 (Box 2A, Videocassette 52)
    [From original finding aid]: includes shot list (NOTE: also on Compilation tape no. 7)
  - Videotapes: Video-D - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic); master, 1983 June (Box 2A, Videocassette 53)
    [From original finding aid]: with complete audio dub
  - Videotapes: Video-D - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-Matic); master, 1983 June (Box 1B, Videocassette 54)
    [From original finding aid]: master dub from 1 inch without complete audio
  - Videotapes: Video-D - 1 reel (1 inch); master, 1983 June (Box 1A, Reel 55)
    [From original finding aid]: time coded, unmixed audio. (NOTE: on Compilation tape no. 7 and Performance Pastiche). Directed by Jack Guidone; written by Alexandra Boris; video by Video Free Earth; music by Zach Swagger and Terrene Currier; starring Kryztov Lindquist, Fredella Calloway, Matt Miller. A multi-media exploration of life in the near future. Uses music and video to tell the story of an android physicist, his wife and robot and their efforts to carve their own niche in the high-tech world of the next century
  - Videotapes: Video Salon I - 1 cassette (3/4 inch U-matic), 1984-1987 (Box 1B, Videocassette 56)